<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pattern collection="welie" patternID="combined-menu" xmlns="http://www.welie.com/plml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.welie.com/plml.xsd">

<name>Header-less Menu</name>

<author>Martijn van Welie</author>

<problem>Users need to access the main sections of the site
</problem>

<illustration><img src="images/emerce.png" border="1"/><br/>From 
<a href="http://www.emerce.nl">www.emerce.nl</a> 
<br/></illustration><br/>

<context>The information 
structure of the site has two or more parts. The main part serves the primary 
purpose of the site. The other parts are more or less independent of the main 
part and serve a secondary purpose. The main part typically has too many 
sections for a horizontal menu and must therefore be displayed vertically. Most 
users will need to see the main part first. </context>

<pattlet>Combine menus in a vertical menu using different visual 
clues instead of headers 
</pattlet>


<solution>The main part is placed at the top and has an accent visually so that 
it is perceived as the main part of the site. The other parts have a modest 
appearance so that they do not compete for attention with the main part. 
<br/> <img src="images/combined-ex.png"/> <br/><a href="wireframes/combined-menu.ppt">&gt; open wireframe &lt;</a></solution>

<rationale>Since the main part contains many items, it should be displayed
vertically. This rules out a horizontal menu for the remaining parts so they
must be displayed vertically as well. The vertical order and the visual design
are important to communicate the differences in importance. An important
advantage is the fact that no separate headings are needed for the parts.
</rationale>

<example>This example from the Financieel Dagblad site shows two sections. <br/>
<img src="images/fd.png"/>
</example>

<uses>
<a href="http://www.fd.nl">www.fd.nl</a>;
</uses>

<references>Consider a combination of horizontal menu and a right-hand vertical
menu when the main section is small.
</references>
</pattern>