<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pattern collection="welie" patternID="split-navigation" xmlns="http://www.welie.com/plml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.welie.com/plml.xsd">

<name>Split Navigation</name>
<author>Gijs de Ridder</author>
<problem>The users need to navigate a hierarchical structure 
</problem>

<principle>
</principle>

<context>Hierarchal structure that consists of 4 levels, content on levels 2-4. Split navigation is a variation of <pattern-link type="is-alternative" patternID="directory"/>. It's important to quickly switch between pages on levels 3 and 4. There is no need to quickly switch between pages on levels 1 and 2. No content on level 1
</context>

<pattlet>Break up the hierarchy in two separate page layouts
</pattlet>

<solution>The hierarchy is broken up in a <i>start</i> page and a <i>topic</i> page. 
The start-page contains levels 1 and 2 (links) of the hierarchy. By clicking a 
link, one can navigate directly to a level 2 topic page. This "topic page" 
contains an index with levels 3 and 4. All textual information is shown on 
this topic page. Users can switch between pages on levels 3 and 4 by 
clicking on the index links. Additionally, <pattern-link type="contains" patternID="crumbs"/> are used to give feedback about the structure and to go back to the first page.
<br/><br/>
Start page
<br/>
<img src="images/4-level-example1.gif"/>
<br/>
Topic Page
<br/>
<img src="images/4-level-example2.gif"/>
</solution>

<rationale>By breaking up the hierarchy in two page layout the first level is basically chopped off after the first selection. The result is a 3 level page that is easy to navigate. The bread crumb allows the users to go back to the first page.
</rationale>

<example><img src="images/monsterboard-4-level.png"/><br/>
This example from the monsterboard shows the Topic page complete with bread crumb.
</example>

<impact/>

<uses><a href="http://www.monsterboard.nl">www.monsterboard.nl</a>
</uses>
<references>This pattern uses the <a href="crumbs.html">Bread Crumb</a> pattern.
</references>
</pattern>