<?xml version="1.0"?>

<pattern collection="welie" patternID="help-wizard" xmlns="http://www.welie.com/plml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.welie.com/plml.xsd">

<name>Help Wizard</name>
<author>Martijn van Welie</author>
<problem>Users need help on a certain topic related to site or when they need to find a specific page in the site.
</problem>


<context>Users need to help on a topic they don't know too much about and they cannot find the information they need by any other way. Typically for site that provide product/service support.<br/>
<br/>
Alternatively, it can also be used as a more 'guided' version of <pattern-link type="generalization" patternID="advanced-search"/>. On  large informative sites with hundreds of pages, it can be beneficial for novice users to get some help.. Such sites will already have complex navigation systems, probably including <pattern-link type="generalization" patternID="advanced-search"/>, <pattern-link type="is-alternative" patternID="sitemap"/> or <pattern-link type="is-alternative" patternID="site-index"/>. In such cases, the Help Wizard can provide some focused and guided searching.
</context>

<illustration><img src="images/helpwiz-sprint-small.png" border="1"/><br/>From 
<a href="http://csb.sprint.com/home/local/techSupport/help_wiz_intro.html">www.sprint.com</a><br/> 
</illustration>

<pattlet>Use a wizard to identify the topic and set the scope for which the users need help. Then show the possible results in the last step.
</pattlet>


<solution>A Help Wizard is a <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="wizard"/> where the users first have to specify what it is they need to know/have/find. Once the topic and scope has been set, the possible solutions/results/files are being presented in the last step. The results are given in a similar way as <pattern-link type="contains" patternID="search-results"/> are given. The main difference is that the number op results should be very limited so that <pattern-link type="not-related" patternID="paging"/> is not needed. <br/>
<br/>
The actual design of the <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="wizard"/> comes on two flavors: a) using multiple screens with next/previous links b) all options numbered in one screen. It depends on the number of options per step you have as well as the amount or screen estate available.
</solution>

<rationale>A Help Wizard is not the same a Search. The Help Wizard only covers a small range of topics and is therefore short and focused. It is almost like a drilling down in a small about of hierarchical information.
</rationale>

<example><img src="images/helpwiz-surveyor.png" border="1"/>
And one example where everything is done in one screen....
<img src="images/helpwiz-ontrack.png" border="1"/>
</example>

<uses>www.surveyor.com; www.sprint.com; www.ontrack.com
</uses>

<references>
</references>
</pattern>
