<?xml version="1.0"?>

<pattern collection="welie" patternID="view" xmlns="http://www.welie.com/plml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.welie.com/plml.xsd">

<name>View</name>
<author>Martijn van Welie</author>
<problem>Users need to manage a collection of objects
</problem>


<context>Typically used in a <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="application"/> in which 'Views' are the main elements. Users need to manage objects such as emails, bank accounts,  stocks, orders and so on. 
</context>

<illustration><img src="images/view-hotmail.gif" border="1"/><br/>From 
<a href="http://www.hotmail.com">www.hotmail.com</a><br/> 
</illustration>

<pattlet>Create an overview of objects that together is meaningful to users
</pattlet>


<solution>A view usually is an overview of a set of objects, e.g. email messages, orders, appointments, products, image, . When views are editable, they may take the form of a <pattern-link type="contains" patternID="list-builder"/> or a list of thumbnails or a custom-designed overview. Views usually contain 'abbreviated' description of the objects themselves. These descriptions are usually clickable which results in a detailed view of the object. Closing the detailed view takes users back to the view itself. Views are typically placed in the <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="center-stage"/> of the page. When views are very large, some form of <pattern-link type="contains" patternID="paging"/> or <pattern-link type="contains" patternID="stepping"/> can be used. Switching from one view to another is done using the <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="main-navigation"/>.<br/>
<br/>
<img src="images/view-wf.gif" border="0"/><br/>
Typical behavior with forms consists of 'view-edit-return'. The user selects an item in the view and edits the detailed description using a <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="forms"/> and/or a <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="wizard"/>. Once the editing is completed, the users is presented with the view again.
</solution>

<rationale>A view is sort of a 'safe place' from which all kinds of 'management' functionality can be used. It gives users the overview they need and it is obvious how users can access the management functionality.
</rationale>

<example>At <a href="http://www.vodafone.nl">www.vodafone.nl</a> can manage a collection of MMS-es. An overview is given from which users can 'copy', 'move', 'view', or 'delete' MMS-es.<br/><img src="images/view-mmsalbum.gif" border="1"/>
</example>

<uses>
</uses>

<references>
</references>
</pattern>
