<?xml version="1.0"?>

<pattern collection="welie" patternID="comparison" xmlns="http://www.welie.com/plml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.welie.com/plml.xsd">

<name>Product Comparison</name>
<author>Martijn van Welie</author>
<problem>The users need to compare similar products
</problem>

<illustration><img src="images/comparison-matrox.png" border="1"/><br/>From 
<a href="http://www.matrox.com">www.matrox.com</a><br/> 
</illustration>

<context>Shopping sites, company products, auctioning sites. The users have 
arrived at a product page or they have reached a list of products. Now they need 
to decide for the product or for similar products. Users may differ in what they 
consider important of a product. Users must be able to easily compare individual 
features of the product. Products may differ in attributes. </context>

<pattlet>Show a matrix of products and features
</pattlet>


<solution>Show the features on the rows of the matrix and the products in the
columns. If a feature is present, mark it. Otherwise don't mark it. If the
feature has specific interesting data for users, show the data instead of the
mark.
<br/>
If there are many features, they can be grouped so that users can select which
aspects they want to compare. When there are many products to compare, let users
select which products they want compare. This can be done in one page when there
are not so many products, otherwise it is done in two steps.
<br/>
<img src="images/comparison-wf.png"/>
<br/>
 <a href="wireframes/comparison.ppt">&gt; open
 wireframe &lt;</a>
</solution>

<rationale>The product/features matrix gives immediate overview and facilitates
easy comparison. By only marking available features visual clutter is minimized.
</rationale>

<example>This example from <a href="http://www.expedia.com">www.expedia.com</a> nicely combines a product comparison with <pattern-link type="is-contained-by" patternID="search"/> results. A search result can be selected for comparison and by clicking the link "compare selected cruises" the comparison is show. At the comparison screen itself, users can deselect one.<br/>
<img src="images/expedia1.gif" border="1"/><br/>
<img src="images/expedia2.gif" border="1"/><br/>
An example from <a 
href="http://www.creative.com">www.creative.com</a> with a selector for the 
aspects and models:<br/> <img src="images/comparison-
3dblaster.png"/><br/> and an example from <a 
href="http://www.creative.com">www.mcafee.com</a>:<br/> 
<img src="images/comparison-mcafee.png"/> </example>

<uses>www.3dblaster.com</uses>

<references>
</references>
</pattern>
